<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Elliot Millington</title>
    <link>https://elliotmillington.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://elliotmillington.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Elliot Millington</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 13:29:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://elliotmillington.github.io/images/icon_hu1c6436ea0a3d4bbf86936c0b03a04d16_61091_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Elliot Millington</title>
      <link>https://elliotmillington.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/neural-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:33:51 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/neural-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have used the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tensorflow.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tensor Flow&lt;/a&gt; library developed by Google to train several artificial neural networks in categorisation tasks. The most developed of these is a network trained to distinguish whether noisy gabor patches were vertical or horizontal, pictured below. This is a replication of a paper by Bertone, Mottron, Jelenic, &amp;amp; Faubert (2005) which found that autistic people were better than typically developing people at some versions of their task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Figure_1a.png&#34; alt=&#34;noisy gabor patches&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then injected internal noise into the model when testing on a test set of data. By comparing the effects of different levels of internal and external noise, I demonstrated a proof-of-concept that different levels of noise will have effects on performance that are not necessarily intuitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My most recent project using neural networks involves using the Tensor Flow framework to make inferences about drawing styles using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/googlecreativelab/quickdraw-dataset&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Quick, Draw!&lt;/a&gt; dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;References&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bertone, A., Mottron, L., Jelenic, P., &amp;amp; Faubert, J. (2005). Enhanced and diminished visuo-spatial information processing in autism depends on stimulus complexity. &lt;em&gt;Brain, 128&lt;/em&gt;(10), 2430–2441. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/brain/awh561&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1093/brain/awh561&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Learning Environments</title>
      <link>https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/ux-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 15:52:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/ux-design/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with the School of Education and Information Services at the University of Glasgow, I worked to improve the user experience of students undertaking fully online courses. I did this through a combination of A/B testing, eye-tracking data, and interviews. I then produced a report with recommendations for improvements which were implemented for the 2020 academic year and online teaching pivot.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural Comparison</title>
      <link>https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/culture-comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 11:16:13 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/culture-comparison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The starting point for this project was trying to understand how autism presents itself throughout the population. Is it a spectrum with everyone on it, or are autistic people their unique group? As a result of the COVID-19 outbreak, all participant recruitment was suspended. As such, I reached out to all researchers who had ever used the Glasgow Sensory Questionnaire. These researchers gave me access to data from tens of thousands of participants from countries all of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Handling this amount of data from diverse sources came with challenges, however, I performed our intended analyses. A paper is currently being written and should be published as a pre-print shortly. A preview of our expected results can be seen below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;All_Net_West.svg&#34; alt=&#34;network of autistic traits and sensory sensitivities&#34;&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;AQ_Distribution_West.svg&#34; alt=&#34;histogram and density plot of autistic traits&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PISA Shiny App</title>
      <link>https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/pisa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 11:47:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/pisa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Programme for International Student Assessment (PISA) is a long running study by the OECD looking at the educational performance of 15-year-olds across the world. With funding from the Erasmus+ Programme, I developed an app analysing the data from the 600,000 students who took part in the 2018 tests. This app fulfils a dual purpose of being a learning aid for complex statistics as well as being a well-founded analysis of how Governments can affect educational outcomes. While the app continues to develop, an early version is currently being hosted &lt;a href=&#34;https://r.qhelp.eu/Glasgow/FormalModels/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Psephography</title>
      <link>https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/psephography/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/psephography/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Beginning from the leadership election of the Labour Party in 2016, this project has developed to take a broader vision of the political geography of the UK. This involves the publishing of our own work on our &lt;a href=&#34;https://psephography.wordpress.com/blog/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CLPNominations&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; accounts, as well as working with the data journalism teams of mainstream media outlets including the BBC, Financial Times, and New Statesman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most popular productions are still the crowd-sourced reporting of internal Labour Party elections, and the subsequent maps showing the results. Some examples of the content produced are below.&lt;/p&gt;








  
  


&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/psephography/gallery/Deputy-Leadership-Standard.jpg&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/psephography/gallery/Deputy-Leadership-Standard_hub8cccdf18da7527fdebf21629edd49ac_1344803_0x190_resize_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;269&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/psephography/gallery/Ei_fviLXcAAovhL.jpg&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/psephography/gallery/Ei_fviLXcAAovhL_hu197b8b464979178b1a1765fa807effc9_459987_0x190_resize_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;111&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/psephography/gallery/Leadership-Map-Hex.jpg&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://elliotmillington.github.io/project/psephography/gallery/Leadership-Map-Hex_hu13672e9ddb73d39f0bc90faf6c671d7f_366555_0x190_resize_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;146&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  

  
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on &#39;The Weirdest People in the World&#39;</title>
      <link>https://elliotmillington.github.io/post/2021/weirdest-people-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 13:29:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://elliotmillington.github.io/post/2021/weirdest-people-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When reading methodological papers, I will often come across something and then never be able to not notice it when it appears. The most recent example of this is the framing of different psychological experiments. When reading a study looking at undergraduates in a European or English-speaking university, the framing will be that the identified effect is universal. Alternatively, if a study is conducted in East Asia, it will be published in a cultural psychology journal and the conclusions will be restricted to the country in question. Studies being completed anywhere else are very rare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Henrich&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Weirdest People in the World&amp;rdquo; is an exploration of how psychological principles that we take for granted are unique to Western, Education, Industrialised, Rich, and Democratic (WEIRD) populations. There have been plenty of comparisons made between this book and &amp;lsquo;Guns, Germs, and Steel&amp;rsquo; by Jared Diamond with both attempting to tackle the question of why Europe came to dominate the world during the 18th and 19th centuries despite being a cultural backwater for the previous 1000 years. However, while &amp;lsquo;Guns, Germs, and Steel&amp;rsquo; looked at the geography and biosphere on each of the continents, Henrich explores how the European psychological trends may have changed the institutional structures within their societies and therefore altered their aggregate trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few different axioms underpin the book, each of which seems to make intuitive sense to me, though I had not considered them before. The first is that it is possible to think about cultural differences on a spectrum. Rather than having distinctly individualistic and collectivistic countries, some cultures will be more individualistic than others. There will always be some discrete differences, such as the choice of numbering system or writing style, though globalisation and language hybridisation is blending even these. Henrich tends to use WEIRD versus non-weird as his metric, operationalised using various psychological measures and rates of cousin marriage, however, I expect that there are more factors to consider than just this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second premise is that different cultures will compete with each other to be the most prosperous. Less successful cultures will either collapse or integrate with the more successful ones, whether deliberately or not. I have seen this compared to Social Darwinism, though I believe this is an unfair comparison. Culture by definition is the learned values, customs, and behaviours from those around you and is therefore not static. The process of learning is inherently trying to find more effective ways of doing things, which should be equally possible when applied to groups of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the common themes of successful cultures that Henrich mentions is the ability to maintain a cohesive social order. According to some research looking at the rise and fall of villages in Indonesia, it is likely that the maximum size for a group to reach without disintegrate is in the low hundreds. Any more than that and disputes can no longer be easily papered over. Not coincidentally, this is close to the maximum number of people that even city-dwellers will semi-regularly interact with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strongest mechanism observed by Henrich was the use of communal rituals, especially those which involve song and dance. Something about the shared experience, sound, and body movement encourages the individual to see their own goals as aligned with the whole community. Having lived through the impact of COVID on our society for the last year, I can see that many of these principals still apply. For example, &amp;lsquo;clap for carers&amp;rsquo; seemed to morph into a ritual by the time it came to an end, with people rushing to participate even if it was not always appreciated by its nominal recipients. Similarly, the prioritisation of group singing in religious services despite concerns of it being the perfect candidate for super-spreading events makes sense when considered as a significant event for community cohesion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final underpinning concept is an appreciation of the magnitude of the effect that culture has on development before and after birth. This can be considered most simply at the behavioural level where some behaviours will be rewarded and therefore repeated. At the same time, our culture will be affecting our value judgements and therefore what would be considered a reward or punishment. For example, there is nothing inevitable about the value of a cell in a spreadsheet being a good outcome or that being boiled in oil in the afterlife is something to be avoided. These abstract concepts have a very real effect on our biology. Henrich demonstrates this using the example that people taught to read use part of their fusiform face area, meaning that they are less effective at face recognition tasks. It is difficult to fully appreciate the effect our culture has on us and our psyche as we have never experienced anything else, nor likely come into contact with anything radically different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the book and its reviews concentrate on the potential role of the Catholic Church and its family program. This set of policies, variously modified and implemented over centuries and geography, expanded the definition of incest beyond what was used in the rest of the world. For example, Henrich found that in the &lt;em&gt;Decretum Gratiani&lt;/em&gt; of 1140, marriages between any more closely related than sixth cousins were banned. This means that you were unable to marry anyone who shared a 5th level grandparent, or over 8000 people! It is unlikely that this prohibition was fully embraced, but its principle will have contributed to the disintegration of kin networks in areas with a strong Catholic presence. The theory then goes that the psychological effects of Catholicism were accelerated by Protestantism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the historical context was interesting, I was most drawn to the psychological trends that Henrich was trying to explain. Most of these will be familiar to anyone who has a passing interest in psychology. For example, differences in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.simplypsychology.org/fundamental-attribution.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;fundamental attribution error&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.simplypsychology.org/asch-conformity.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;conformity&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.simplypsychology.org/kohlberg.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;morality&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.simplypsychology.org/social-identity-theory.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;identity&lt;/a&gt;, and analytical versus holistic thinking were all explored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, there were other phenomena which differed by cultured that I was not familiar with. First off, and especially embarrassing given my familiarity with psychophysics, were changes in low-level sensory processing. &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.mit.edu/allanmc/www/socialperception14.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Segall et al. (1986)&lt;/a&gt; identified that US undergraduates were the most vulnerable to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M%C3%BCller-Lyer_illusion&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Müller-Lyer illusion&lt;/a&gt;, while participants in Johannesburg were not affected by the illusion. Even in 1986, it was suggested that this was the result of the type of environments that participants were looking at when their visual system was developing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another set of experiments I was surprised by were the studies which are generally used in economics as part of game theory. These tasks involve two participants interacting with each other in a very controlled way. For example, one participant could be given £5 and then asked how much they wanted to share with the other person. Intuitively, I expected more individualistic people to be less cooperative in this style of task. Instead, the consistent theme was that participants from Europe and the US were the most likely to trust complete strangers. They would also be more likely to punish anyone who refused to cooperate, even if that came at a personal cost. Meanwhile, participants from non-WEIRD countries were more likely to take more resources for themselves and find it acceptable when others short-changed them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final example I want to share is the applicability of the concept of personality. The model of personality which has been generally accepted is Costa and McCrae&amp;rsquo;s Big Five: openness, contentiousness, extravertism, agreeableness, and neuroticism. Henrich suggests that this is a distinctly WEIRD way of thinking about people as it assumes there is a true self which will behave in predictable ways in any situation, rather than adapting to the given context. As such, in a study of the Tsimane&#39; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4104167/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gurven et al (2013)&lt;/a&gt;, it was found that the only factors of personality which could be justified were roughly pro-sociality and industriousness. I found this hilarious because, in my undergraduate, I was taught about &lt;a href=&#34;http://gosling.psy.utexas.edu/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/CDPS99Xspeciesreview.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; that said that the Big Five had been successfully applied to a variety of species which included the octopus. My extensive scientific training suggests that it is unlikely that personalities were inherited by molluscs but skipped over the people of Bolivia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is especially notable about each of the experiments that Henrich goes through is that they are many of the &amp;lsquo;classic&amp;rsquo; studies of psychology, so well replicated that it was assumed that they were stable constructs that could be relied upon. Instead, it now appears that they are only the foundations of our WEIRD psychology and can only really be applied to a very small sub-population of the world, let alone the humans of history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sheer number of tasks would make this post too long if I were to describe each of them one by one, however, a good summary is freely available &lt;a href=&#34;http://hci.ucsd.edu/102b/readings/WeirdestPeople.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several obvious objections to the premises of the book. The most notable of these is how it deliberately skips over Europe&amp;rsquo;s exploitation of much of the rest of the world. In a limited sense, I think that this can be justified - most of the processes will have been taking effect before the age of colonisation and will have influenced its course. However, to then talk about the rate of technological innovation in the industrial revolution without mentioning it feels like academic neglect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, no matter how many experimental tasks described, the key argument that the Catholic Church was the key institution which led to Europe&amp;rsquo;s dominance can only be tested using retrospective evidence. Undeniably, the evidence Henrich provides is compelling and often goes into granular detail which I did not think possible. However, I remain unsure about how large that effect will be when compared to everything that has happened over the last two thousand years. Unfortunately, as with any research of this kind, these tools are all that is left to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was difficult to read this book and maintain a critical eye throughout. This was mostly because I suspect I am at the extreme end of the WEIRD mindset distribution. For example, I am very time conscious, packing as many scheduled activities in my day as possible. Similarly, working in academia means that there is no alternative to the analytical thinking style. I also had to be conscious of not slipping into convenient but unhelpful heuristics such as thinking about the &amp;lsquo;noble savage&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than anything else, Henrich&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Weirdest People in the World&amp;rdquo; is a thought-provoking book, providing a good overview of modern psychology and its historical context. It also raises important points about how Western scientists should consider how they frame their research and think more about the people participating in their studies. It&amp;rsquo;s following of the Catholic Church and its spread over the world offers an enjoyable narrative to traverse all of the different scientific fields, even if that narrative is not as strong as it may be portrayed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Portfolio</title>
      <link>https://elliotmillington.github.io/portfolio/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://elliotmillington.github.io/portfolio/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
