<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>big data | Elliot Millington</title>
    <link>https://ElliotMillington.github.io/tag/big-data/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ElliotMillington.github.io/tag/big-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>big data</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 11:47:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ElliotMillington.github.io/images/icon_hu86028ebfd8bd1ff90892765b740400b4_78559_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>big data</title>
      <link>https://ElliotMillington.github.io/tag/big-data/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural Comparison</title>
      <link>https://ElliotMillington.github.io/project/culture-comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 11:16:13 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ElliotMillington.github.io/project/culture-comparison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The starting point for this project was trying to understand how autism presents itself throughout the population. Is it a spectrum with everyone on it, or are autistic people their unique group? As a result of the COVID-19 outbreak, all participant recruitment was suspended. As such, I reached out to all researchers who had ever used the Glasgow Sensory Questionnaire. These researchers gave me access to data from tens of thousands of participants from countries all of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Handling this amount of data from diverse sources came with challenges, however, I performed our intended analyses. A paper is currently being written and should be published as a pre-print shortly. A preview of our expected results can be seen below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;All_Net_West.svg&#34; alt=&#34;network of autistic traits and sensory sensitivities&#34;&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;AQ_Distribution_West.svg&#34; alt=&#34;histogram and density plot of autistic traits&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PISA Shiny App</title>
      <link>https://ElliotMillington.github.io/project/pisa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 11:47:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ElliotMillington.github.io/project/pisa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Programme for International Student Assessment (PISA) is a long running study by the OECD looking at the educational performance of 15-year-olds across the world. With funding from the Erasmus+ Programme, I developed an app analysing the data from the 600,000 students who took part in the 2018 tests. This app fulfils a dual purpose of being a learning aid for complex statistics as well as being a well-founded analysis of how Governments can affect educational outcomes. While the app continues to develop, an early version is currently being hosted &lt;a href=&#34;https://r.qhelp.eu/Glasgow/FormalModels/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
